<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The praise of humility a sermon preached upon the 20th of March 1687 : being Palm-Sunday, at the Guild-Hall-chappel, London / by John Turner ...</title>
            <author>Turner, John, b. 1649 or 50.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63914</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3314</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10525</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11818625</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11818625</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49557</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63914)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49557)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 554:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The praise of humility a sermon preached upon the 20th of March 1687 : being Palm-Sunday, at the Guild-Hall-chappel, London / by John Turner ...</title>
                  <author>Turner, John, b. 1649 or 50.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, and are to be sold by Randal Taylor ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Humility --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49557:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PRAISE OF HUMILITY.</p>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED Upon the <hi>20th.</hi> of <hi>March</hi> 1687.</p>
            <p>BEING Palm-Sunday, AT The <hi>Guild-Hall</hi>-Chappel, <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN TVRNER</hi> Hoſpitaller of St. <hi>Thomas Southwark.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed, and are to be Sold by <hi>Randal Taylor</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall.</hi> 1687.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:49557:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49557:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Right Honorable, and my ſingular Good Lord, <hi>George</hi> Lord <hi>Jeffries,</hi> Baron of <hi>Wem,</hi> Lord High Chancellor of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and one of His Majeſties moſt Honorable Privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis Sermon, which for the great ſeaſonableneſs of the Subject of it, I think it my Duty to Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh at this time, it being Preached, as it fell out, but juſt the day before His Majeſty was pleaſed to ſignifie His Gracious Reſolution, to allow Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to all his loving Subjects of what Denomination ſoever: I do humbly beſeech your Lordſhip to Accept and Patronize, as you do the Author; and give me leave at once to pay a very ſmall and inconſiderable Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for many the moſt ſignal and obliging Favors, and to ſhelter ſo lovel y,ſo uſeful, and ſo excellent a Vertue un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſhady Patronage of ſo great a Perſon, whoſe Name and Authority, will at the ſame time render it more Charming to its Friends, and make it appear ſo formida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to its Enemies, that it will conſtrain and force them into its own reſemblance, and cauſe them to Abaſe and Humble themſelves before it.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:49557:3"/>
            <p>But beſides the plain ſuitableneſs of the Diſcourſe to the Juncture, Humility and Charity, being the only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedients that can make Liberty ſafe, or Toleration a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable thing, by preventing thoſe Quarrels and Animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities that ariſe from different ſentiments in Religious matters. Beſides my own particular and perſonal Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, which I cannot think of without ſhame, when I conſider how little I deſerve them; there is alſo a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruity in the Subject of my Sermon, to your Lordſhips Perſon, which ſeems to me to challenge and ſingle you out for a Patron, without asking any leave but from the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of things, I mean thoſe Natural effects of this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable Vertue which I have recommended, which flow ſo eaſily, ſo unaffectedly from you, with ſo much Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Brightneſs, with ſo much Strength and Vigor, and with ſo conſtant and uninterrupted a Stream, in the ſweetneſs and affability of your Converſation, even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong your Inferiors and Dependants, in the eaſineſs of Acceſs in the midſt of ſo much Greatneſs, the Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the Juſtice, the Sagacity of diſpatch in ſo impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate a crowd of Buſineſs, all which would be certain and infallible Indications at once of a Generous and Compoſed Mind, a Great and Lofty, and yet an Humble Spirit, though they were not, as they are, attended with a peculiar proneneſs to Forgive the moſt implacable and mortal Enemies, of which your Lordſhip hath given ſuch convincing Proofts, that this alone might be ſufficient, with out that univerſal Merit, which even Envy and Detracti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on cannot help allowing you, to recommend you Powerfully to the Favor of a Prince, in whom Mercy is Hereditary, and Majeſty is by Nature temper'd with Pity and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, to render it more eaſie and familiar to his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: But there is likewiſe the Juſtice and Integrity, the Conſtancy and Courage, the Diligence and Aſſiduity, the Wiſdom and the Condu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t of your Actions, that have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curr'd
<pb facs="tcp:49557:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> and club'd with a kind and obliging Temper, to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der you truly Great, and make you an Object worthy the Eſteem of two the moſt Judicious and Diſcerning Kings that ever ſat upon the Engliſh Throne.</p>
            <p>And, my Lord, it is another genuine Effect of that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable Vertue which is the Glorious Theme of the enſuing Papers, that it makes its way to Greatneſs, as your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip hath done, not by Popularity and miſchievous In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigues, to the Danger, if not Ruin of the publick Peace, but only by juſt Actions and honorable Deſigns, and like your Great Maſter, whom Providence had a mind to ſhew how much it loved, by the Protection of a <hi>weakly Bark,</hi> when the <hi>Royal Oak</hi> was unable to defend Him, you Ventured, Suffered, and Eſcaped a Shipwreck, and made a coſtly Sacrifice of your Hopes and Fortunes to the publick Good, before your entrance upon that Scene of Honor in which you now ſhine, with ſo much the greater Brightneſs, for having firſt ſuffered ſo Glorious an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe; by this means ſhewing at once, the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt your Enemies and you, and verifying our Saviours never failing Promiſe to all his Faithful Followers and Diſciples, that <hi>whoſoever Exalteth himſelf,</hi> by Baſe, Diſhonorable, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nworthy Means, <hi>the ſame ſhall be Abaſed, and he that Humbleth himſelf ſhall be Exalted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For Humility, my Lord, is the true way to Greatneſs; it is not a <hi>Poltron</hi> and a ſneaking Diſpoſition, as its Name may ſeem unjuſtly to Inſinuate; but it implies Magnanimity and Courage at the ſame time, by looking backward upon God, and inwards upon it Self, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards upon the Hope and Expectation of a future Life; it acquires an habitual Senſe and Sympathy of Human Frailty, a Pity and Compaſſion for Human want and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, an univerſal Candor, Integrity and Ingenuity, in all its Words and Actions, and Deſignes, a warm in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination to promote the good of its Country, and the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs
<pb facs="tcp:49557:4"/> of Mankind, an admiration of God, and a deſire to be like him, and a ſcorn of every thing that is unhand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome or unjuſt. It cannot revenge its own wrongs upon the Public, it cannot embarraſs or embroil the World upon a principle of Private Intereſt; it cannot climb to Greatneſs upon the ruins of Juſtice, though it would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo fain, but it ſtill meets with ſomething that pulls it ſtrongly back, and rewards all Ambition with regret and pain, but what is noble, and uſeful, and ſerviceable to the World, and is an Inſtinct of the Divinity in Human Nature, to prompt it, when fair Opportunities preſent themſelves, to great Atchievements and generous <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings; it Aſcends by the Steps of <hi>Chancery</hi> into the Temple of <hi>Honor,</hi> and from the Pinacle of that lofty Structure, it Surveys the whole Extent and Circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of things; and will not fall down to Worſhip a mean deſign, to Purchaſe all the Proſpect that it Views.</p>
            <p>But, my Lord, I grow troubleſome with too much length; and therefore if what I have ſaid, may not be allow'd to be Apology ſufficient, for the hardineſs of this Addreſs, I ſhall only beg, that what I cannot Juſtifie, you would pleaſe to Pardon; and with my Prayers to God for your Lordſhips Health and Happineſs, and encreaſe of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor. I am, may it it pleaſe your Lordſhip,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt Humble. Grateful, and Obedient Servant. John Turner.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:49557:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Collect for <hi>Palm-Sunday.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>ALmighty and Everlaſting God, who of thy tender Love towards Mankind, haſt ſent thy Son, our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Jeſus Chriſt, to take upon him our Fleſh, and to ſuffer Death upon the Croſs, that all Mankind ſhould follow the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of his great Humility; Merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully grant that we may both follow the Example of his Patience, and alſo be made partakers of his Reſurrection, through the ſame Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:49557:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49557:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Matth. 5. 3.</bibl>
               <q>Bleſſed are the poor in Spirit, for theirs is the Kingdom of Heaven.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this and the two following Chapters, which contain our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours admirable Sermon upon the Mount, to his Diſciples, there is drawn, as it were in little, the lively Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traiture of a Chriſtian Man in all his Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, ſo that if we could once prevail up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our ſelves, frail and diſobedient Creatures as we are, to live up to the height and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of thoſe Rules, which are here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed and laid down, there could be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing wanting to make us abſolutely and compleatly happy, both in Body and Soul. For if we Survey this whole Diſcourſe, tho but with a careleſs and ſuperficial Eye, yet it will be eaſie to perceive, at firſt ſight, that it is exactly Calculated, for the happineſs of Mankind, to render us the moſt pleaſant and contented within our ſelves, the moſt ſecure
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49557:6"/> from any fear and danger from without, and to procure us the mutual Favor and Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of each other, in all our honeſt deſigns and undertakings.</p>
            <p>To demonſtrate this in all the ſeveral in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, ſo plainly, and ſo particularly as it might, and as it ought to be done, the more effectually to ſhew the manifeſt uſefulneſs and tendency of them all, to ennoble and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove our Natures, and to make us as Wiſe, as Healthful, and as Happy, as we are ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally capable of being, is not the buſineſs of a ſingle Sermon, but of a large, Elaborate and Comprehenſive Volume, wherein Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Philoſophy may have room enough to ſtretch themſelves at length, and appear in their full Magnitude and Juſt Proportion; therefore I ſhall content my ſelf at preſent, without launching out into ſo large a Field, where every new Fruit and Flower will af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford us a plentiful Entertainment by it ſelf; to confine my ſelf within a much narrower compaſs, by devoting my whole Diſcourſe to the conſideration of one Subject, and laying the ſingle Charms of Humility be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you: Humility, that Vertue which we ſo much want, Humility the Queen of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth, the fair and Majeſtick So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49557:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> of all Chriſtian Graces, to which the firſt Beatitude was deſervedly vouchſafed, to which as being the Corner-ſtone of Wiſdom, the Bottom and Foundation of all other Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and Goodly diſpoſitions of Mind, the promiſe of both Worlds is annex't as it's re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, <hi>Bleſſed are the Poor in Spirit,</hi> ſaith our <hi>Saviour, for theirs is the Kingdom of Heaven;</hi> and then again, <hi>v. 5. Bleſſed are the meek, for they ſhall inherit the Earth.</hi> That is, Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility is ſuch a diſpoſition of Mind, as is naturally fitted to give us the trueſt enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this Life, and to prepare us the moſt effectually for that which is to come. It conſiſts in having a ſober and modeſt Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of our ſelves, and in this it is oppoſed to that Arrogant and Swelling Humor which is a manifeſt detraction from all thoſe Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues or Excellencies whatſoever they be, which it pretends to vaunt it ſelf upon. It is likewiſe accompanied with ſuch a kind and charitable Opinion of others, as hath a natural tendency to make all the World our Friends; and it hath this peculiar Excellency in it, that it throws a Veil which no Man will be forward or deſirous to uncover, over all the Frailties, Infirmities, or Imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Men, and to all their Accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49557:7"/> Endowments, and Perfections, it gives an additional Brightneſs and Luſtre, it makes them appear more Shining, and more Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, more Beautiful and Lovely, more In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viteing and Attracting, more worthy of Praiſe, becauſe they do not affect it, more apt to be diſcovered and laid open with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to the publick View, and to the light of the World, becauſe they do not offer and obtrude themſelves upon it, with a proſtitute Sollicitation, but with a Virgin Modeſty and Shame, they ſtrive to withdraw and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal themſelves; and thus it is true likewiſe in the courſe of Nature, as well as in that of Providence, that <hi>God reſiſteth the Proud, but giveth Grace to the Humble,</hi> that is, that Pride is a natural Obſtruction to it ſelf, but Humility hath natural Charms to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it. It does, with reſpect to our ſelves, what Love and Charity are ſaid to do with reference to others, it covers a multitude of Frailties and Offences, and if there be any thing Excellent or Praiſeworthy in us, it ſets it off with a new acceſſion of Beauty and Advantage.</p>
            <p>Humility is ſuch a diſpoſition of Mind, whoſe very Nature conſiſts in a certain plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Calmneſs and Serenity of Spirit, which
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49557:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> is the beſt fitted to enjoy it felf, without which no Moral Vertue or Chriſtian Grace can have it's perfect work in our Hearts, but it will be ruffled and diſcompoſed by the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order of Paſſions, and the uneaſie turbulence of immoderate deſires. It is the proper tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and conſtitution of a Wiſe Man, who being ſtill and quiet, and ſedate within him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, is the better enabled to make a true judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and a right advantage of all other things and perſons round about him. It is ſuch a Vertue, that as it is the beſt way to advance us, and to bring us to a Flouriſhing and Proſperous condition, ſo it makes that Proſperity ſafe and unenvy'd, it carries along with it the good Wiſhes and Prayers of all we converſe with, and all that have any know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of us, that it may continue; and if any affliction or calamity happen to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take us, it will be ſure to ſupply us with Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Relief from without, and within it will furniſh us with Patience and Submiſſion to the Will of God, which are a compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Remedy to the worſt of Evils. It is the moſt certain and unqueſtionable expedient of the utmoſt happineſs in this Life; and it is not only a condition of, but alſo a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary preparation to the Enjoyment and Glory of the other.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:49557:8"/>
            <p>But on the contrary, if inſtead of this, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of enjoying Meekneſs and Poverty of Spirit, which is indeed the only true Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Magnanimity of it; our Saviour had taught his Diſciples after another man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, be ye <hi>Inſolent</hi> and <hi>Proud,</hi> be ye <hi>Haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> and <hi>Aſſuming, Arrogant</hi> and <hi>Overweening, Vaunters</hi> of <hi>your ſelves,</hi> and <hi>Deſpiſers</hi> of <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers;</hi> I need not ſay what Horrid, what Diſmal, what Deplorable Effects the univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal practice of ſuch a Doctrin as this would have brought upon the World; it would have Unhinged the whole Frame and Order of things, and turned the World again into a <hi>Chaos</hi> more confuſed than that out of which by the kind and harmonious diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Divine Nature it was at firſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced; and if to ſo Deſtructive ſo Baneful, ſo Pernicious a Temper, he had annexed the ſame promiſe which he hath done to Meekneſs, for <hi>they</hi> that are thus affected <hi>ſhall Inherit the Earth,</hi> it would have been a plain ſign, he did not underſtand the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural conſequence of his own Doctrin, which can have no other poſſible iſſue or reſult where it is univerſally practiced, but only to bring the World into confuſion, to chafe it with perpetual Strife, Animoſity and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49557:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> to involve it in Blood, and Miſery, and Slaughter, and to make Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind a mutual and an eternal Plague and Puniſhment to each other.</p>
            <p>Or if he had made it a condition of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining an Inheritance in the World to come, or had preſcribed it, as a preparative to the enjoyment of it, we muſt either have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded him to have been the vileſt of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtors, inſtead of being as he is, the Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of the World, and the Redeemer of Mankind, from Miſery as well as Sin; or we muſt have looked upon God Almighty, whoſe Meſſenger he was, under the notion of an angry and revengeful Being, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted in nothing more, than in the Miſery and Torment of his Creatures; for Heaven at this rate would have been ſo far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing worth accepting, being an Eternal State of mutual Pride, Animoſity and Contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that but to think of coming thither, would be a degree of Damnation, even in this Life, and a Torment too great for Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature to bear.</p>
            <p>But if we underſtand any thing of the condition of thoſe Bleſſed Spirits, that are made partakers of the Heavenly Kingdom, and of the Life and Glory that ſhall be reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49557:9"/> it is without all queſtion, or elſe it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be an happy State, a State of mutual Benevolence and Goodwill, it conſiſts in an Eternal Friendſhip, which cannot be ſuppoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in ſo great equality of Happineſs and Glory, and in ſo great and univerſal longing after cloſer and more intimate Communion with God, ſuch breathing and contention after the enjoyment of him, without a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual yielding and condeſcention; it is found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in an humble and modeſt Opinion of themſelves, in a kind and charitable diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition towards their Neighbors, the Part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and fellowpartakers of the ſame Light and Immortality with themſelves, in a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect reſignation to the Divine Will, and in a magnificent Eſteem and veneration of his Nature; and our Saviour by making ſuch habits and diſpoſitions of Mind, to be the indiſpenſible conditions of being his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, by placing all the inſtances of Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in ſuch things as are ſo manifeſtly for the comfort and ſupport of Humane Life; and are withal ſo neceſſary and ſo natural a preparation to the Happineſs of the future State, hath given as great, if not a much greater Teſtimony to the truth of his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin, the Divinity of his Perſon, and the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49557:9"/> unqueſtionable Authority of his Miſſion from above, than any the greateſt of his Miracles, without ſo uſeful and ſo highly reaſonable a Doctrine could have afforded.</p>
            <p>I ſaid juſt now that Humility was the very <hi>Corner-ſtone</hi> of Wiſdom, the <hi>Bottom</hi> and <hi>Foundation</hi> of all manner of Vertue; but upon ſecond Thoughts I recall my ſelf, it is not ſo much the <hi>Foundation</hi> of Vertue as the <hi>Complexion</hi> of it, it comprehends <hi>all</hi> Vertue and Wiſdom within it ſelf. For Vertue is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but practical Wiſdom, and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility is Patience, Humility is Temperance, Humility is Juſtice, Humility is Chaſtity, Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility is Prudence, Humility is Obedience, Humility is Charity, Humility is Brotherly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindneſs, putting on ſeveral Appearances and Shapes that have a diſagreeing likeneſs to each other, like Brothers and Siſters, or the neareſt Kindred of the ſame Houſe and Line, that have a reſemblance and a difference at the ſame time.</p>
            <q>
               <l>— Facies non omnibus una;</l>
               <l>Nec diverſa tamen, qualem decet eſſe Sororum.</l>
            </q>
            <p>For all theſe are founded where they are not practiced by <hi>inſtinct</hi> or by <hi>habit,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:49557:10"/> which two are but <hi>animal</hi> and brutiſh things, even in thoſe Actions that have a vertuous Appearance, I ſay, all theſe are founded, where ever they are exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed upon inducements of Reaſon, which are the only things that conſtitute the Eſſence of Vertue in any particular inſtance that can happen; they are founded in a due ſenſe of the infirmity of Human Nature; For all theſe are neceſſary upon no other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, but either that ſingle Perſons cannot be happy, or elſe that Society cannot ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt without them; the former of which is manifeſtly the caſe of Chaſtity, Temperance and Patience, the latter more remotely of Charity, Brotherly-kindneſs and Prudence, without which a Society cannot ſo well ſubſiſt; more immediately of Obedience and Juſtice, without which it cannot poſſibly ſubſiſt at all; ſo that all theſe Vertues have the conſideration of Human Frailty for their Object, and the redreſſing of it for their end; and this is no other than what we call <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility,</hi> it is a wiſe and a juſt Senſe of the frailty and infirmity to which Human Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is ſubject, ſo that when we ſpeak of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, we ſpeak of every thing that is either truly uſeful or truly ornamental; it is the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophical
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49557:10"/> 
               <hi>Elixir</hi> that converts every thing it touches into Gold; it is the natural and the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litic <hi>Archaeus</hi> that makes and governs the Vital Spirits of Action, that ſweetens and pacifies the diſagreeing Humors both of the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and the civil Body; it is that Univerſal Remedy of Human Life, to which, when we mean it of any thing but this, none but very <hi>Empiricks</hi> and Mountebanks in <hi>Phyſick</hi> are ſo hardy to pretend; it is Milk and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney purchas'd by ſound Wiſdom and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive Judgment without Money and without Price, it is <hi>Health to the Navil and Marrow to the Bones,</hi> it is <hi>Corn, Wine</hi> and <hi>Oyl,</hi> with all their good effects of a <hi>ſtrong</hi> Body, a <hi>ſhining</hi> Countenance, and a <hi>joyful</hi> Heart. <hi>We have ſeen thy goings, O God, we have all ſeen how thou our God and King goeſt in the Sanctuary, the Singers go before, the Miniſtrels follow after, in the midſt are the Damſels play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the Timbrels:</hi> Humility leads up the Dance of Vertue, and Charity concludes it, and in the midſt are Peace and Mercy join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hands together, Righteouſneſs, Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, Obedience, Patience, Magnanimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Prudence, Inviting, Kiſſing and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing each other.</p>
            <p>Humility, thou <hi>meek</hi> &amp; <hi>lowly,</hi> and yet at once
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49557:11"/> 
               <hi>infinite</hi> and <hi>exalted</hi> Vertue! thou comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, incomprehenſible thing! thou that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quereſt by Patience and ſubdueſt by Yielding! <hi>whereunto ſhall I liken</hi> thy divine Perfection? or <hi>with what compariſon ſhall I compare thee?</hi> Humility how lovely? how amiable art thou? <hi>thou art fairer than the Children of</hi> Men, rud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, freſh and beautiful as the Morning Sky, <hi>All thy Garments ſmell of Myrrh, Aloes and Caſſia; Full of Grace are thy Lips, becauſe the Lord hath bleſſed thee for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſource of Humility is not ſo obſcure as that of <hi>Nile</hi> is ſaid to be, but yet it is more impervious and inacceſſible than the other, not but that it diſcovers a great deal of it ſelf, but that it hides much more, for the Fountain of Humility is God himſelf.</p>
            <p>It is a thing very agreeable to the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and reſtleſs Curioſity of Mankind, what we find practiced, even by inquiſitive Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, to be taking things in pieces to ſee what they are made of, and finding it ſelf ſurrounded by ſuch a Magnificent Scene, contrived after ſo uſeful and ſo excellent a manner, adorn'd and <hi>variegated</hi> with ſuch an infinity of beautiful and ſurprizing Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, to be enquiring into the contexture of the Work it ſelf, and into the maker of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49557:11"/> it, and from it ſelf to aſcend higher in the Scale of Cauſes, to the Original and Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of its Being, which is that which we uſe to call by the name of God, in which as being the firſt, the moſt eminent and moſt tranſcendent Cauſe, it diſcerns ſo much Excellence, ſo vaſt, unbounded and unlimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Perfection, that though there be enough and to ſpare of other things, that may be ſufficient to abaſe and humble wiſe Men, as the narrowneſs of our knowledge when it is the moſt improved, the dulneſs and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>activity of our Minds when they are the moſt attentive and erect, the ſcantineſs of our Memories when they are the moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive, the ſhortneſs of our Lives at the utmoſt extremity of that which we call Old Age, the crazineſs of thoſe Bodies which we carry about us when they are at the ſtrongeſt, the Diſeaſes and caſualties to which they are expoſed, the uncertainty of our Fortunes when they are at the higheſt, the ſatiating nature and quality of our Enjoyments when they continue firm and conſtant to us, as we before experiment would have wiſh'd and pray'd they might be, the fickleneſs of Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, the mutability of Intereſt, the decays of Youth and Beauty, the dependency and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxiouſneſs
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49557:12"/> of all Earthly Things; yet theſe are but ſmall diminutions of our ſelves, they create but a low degree of Humility and Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrence in us, in compariſon of what un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidably reſults from the conſideration of God and his infinite Perfection, his immenſe Power, his incomprehenſible Wiſdom, his never failing Goodneſs, his impartial and unbiaſs'd Juſtice, his manifeſt and yet <hi>my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious</hi> Omnipreſence; then we loath and abhor our ſelves in Duſt and Aſhes, we are fill'd with a faſtidious Averſion and Diſlike, we vaniſh away in Smoak, we ſhrink and ſhrivel into nothing, we are not ſo much as a drop to the <hi>Atlantique,</hi> as an <hi>Atome</hi> to the Body of the Sun, or to the whole cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference of <hi>liquid aether,</hi> in which he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms his daily and yearly Motion; we are <hi>metamorphos'd</hi> out of Men to Worms, and out of Worms we are transform'd to Inſects, and when we <hi>conſider the Heavens, the work of his Fingers, the Moon and the Stars which he hath ordained,</hi> it is natural for us to cry out with the <hi>Royal</hi> Poet, who in this was not guilty of Poetique Licence, <hi>Lord, what is Man that thou art mindful of him, or the Son of Man that thou haſt regard unto him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We may conſider this Univerſe under the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49557:12"/> notion of an inverted <hi>Pyramid,</hi> of which the humble Man is the terminating Point and the divine Perfections, are the inverted <hi>Baſis,</hi> and the Lines that are drawn between theſe two from the bottom to the top, grow ſtill more wide and diſtant from each other, as they aſcend higher in their Progreſs to the top, ſo that the humble Mans Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plations begin at himſelf, and from himſelf they aſcend upward thorough all the ſeveral Orders of created Beings, till he comes to the great Source and Original of all things, wherein all their ſeveral Beauties and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections are <hi>tranſcendently</hi> contained, and ſtill the higher he goes the more humble he is, becauſe he diſcerns the more, upon a juſt compariſon, the littleneſs of himſelf; but in the divine Nature he is ſwallowed up with aſtoniſhment and wonder, there is ſo vaſt and infinite a Proſpect before him; he is like a ſmall crany to a vaſt Circumference, though the one may be ſeen and obſerved through the other, and he diſcovers the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Attributes full of excellence and bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and is raviſht with the Senſe and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of them, though he cannot <hi>ſee God as he is</hi> in himſelf, in his true Latitude and juſt Extent, like the Image of ſome large
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49557:13"/> and ſpacious Object, contracted into Minia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, in which all the Parts and Lineaments appear, but not in their natural and true dimenſions. And ſtill the more he Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templates, the Wiſer he grows, and the more he Deſpiſeth himſelf in compariſon of that Excellence he converſes with, the nigher he approaches in perfection to it.</p>
            <p>But with the Proud Man it is clean other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; it is true, he begins with himſelf as well as the other, but then he ends in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf too, his proſpect is not upwards towards Heaven, but downwards towards the Earth, and he ſits at the top of that ſhort inverted <hi>Pyramid</hi> of which himſelf is the <hi>Baſis,</hi> and the broadeſt part, ſo that he converſes with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what is either leſs than himſelf, or what he imagins to be ſo; for no Man certainly can be Proud of the Compariſon, when he thinks himſelf Converſant with a Nobler Object, ſo that it is exactly true of the Proud, Haughty and Aſſuming Man, what <hi>David</hi> ſaith in general of the Wicked, that <hi>he hath not God in all his thoughts,</hi> and that though Pride and Ignorance be not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertible terms, for a Man may be Ignorant that is not Proud, yet Pride is certainly no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but an effect of Ignorance, of want
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49557:13"/> of Conſideration, want of Skill and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the true Rate and Value of things.</p>
            <p>Again, It is not only true that this admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Grace and Vertue of Humility, hath its firmeſt Root, and it's moſt powerful Cauſe in the contemplation of the Divine Nature, which is the moſt excellent Object we can converſe with, but the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> tells us ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, ſpeaking of God himſelf, that <hi>he Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth himſelf to behold the things that are in Heaven and Earth. From the riſing of the Sun,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>unto the going down of the ſame, the Lords Name is to be Praiſed, the Lord is high above all Nations, and his Glory above the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, who is like unto the Lord our God, who dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth on High, and yet Humbleth himſelf to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the things that are in Heaven and Earth?</hi> Not that God who is the <hi>Firſt mover</hi> and the only <hi>Supream</hi> and <hi>Self-exiſtent</hi> Nature, can in propriety be ſaid to be an <hi>Humble</hi> or an <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> being, but that he is inveſted in a moſt eminent manner, with all thoſe gentle incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations to Pity and Compaſſion, which are the Natural conſequents of Humility among Men, he is <hi>kind</hi> and <hi>gracious, ſlow to anger</hi> and <hi>eaſie to be entreated,</hi> and <hi>his Mercy is over all his works,</hi> his <hi>Power</hi> is allay'd and tempered by his <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> and his <hi>Juſtice</hi> is blended by
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49557:14"/> his <hi>Mercy,</hi> and his great <hi>Mind</hi> is thoughtful with the Cares of the Univerſe, which is his <hi>perpetual Charge,</hi> and a <hi>Charge</hi> which cannot be managed by an <hi>Affected</hi> and <hi>Proud,</hi> which is a diſturbance to it ſelf, and would hinder the due adminiſtration of ſo vaſt a Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but by a <hi>Sedate, Quiet</hi> and <hi>Serene</hi> Mind, which is not more requiſite to the Government of the World, than to the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyneſs of the Governor himſelf, who in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to his being infinitely perfect, as he cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly is, as being the cauſe of all things, and containing all Created Perfection within himſelf, muſt in the Firſt place be ſuppoſed to be neceſſarily Exiſtent, for Exiſtence is the root of all other Perfections, and in the next, to be infinitely Happy and perfectly at Eaſe, for where there is no Happyneſs, there is no Enjoyment, and where there is perfect Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyneſs, there muſt be perfect Peace; and if God were not the moſt perfectly Happy, he muſt be the moſt Miſerable and Unhappy Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, becauſe it is true of him, what the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired writer to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> tells us of <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chizedek,</hi> that he is, <hi>without Father, without Mother, without Deſcent</hi> or Genealogy, <hi>he hath neither Beginning of Days, nor End of Life,</hi> but muſt paſs for ever Miſerable thorough a
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49557:14"/> lingering Eternity, and can do all things but die.</p>
            <p>But beſides this, there are four things that diſcover the Nature of God in this ſenſe to be <hi>Humble,</hi> that it is an <hi>Equal,</hi> an <hi>Impaſſible</hi> thing, and that it is never diſturbed out of it's true Poiſe and Balance by any event whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.</p>
            <p>Firſt, There is the Univerſe which is not only ſo regularly Govern'd, as I have ſaid before, but ſo exactly, ſo admirably contrived, which ſpeaks not only a very wiſe and knowing, but a very cool, conſiderate and quiet Artiſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, All Pride and Arrogance pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding out of Ignorance, this cannot be competible to that perfect Nature which is acknowledged to be infinitely Wiſe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, If we examin the ſtate of things among Men, they are compariſons upon the <hi>Level</hi> that uſually make us Proud, for the conſideration of things that are above us is naturally fitted to debaſe and humble our Minds, and when we reflect either upon Beaſts or Flies, upon Creatures of no under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, or Creatures of no moment, we diſdain to come into the compariſon with
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49557:15"/> them, neither do we look upon it as any commendation, it makes no manner of change or alteration in our Viſage, or deportment, to be thought by others, or to think our ſelves more excellent and valuable than ſuch things as theſe. But it is then we begin to <hi>think more highly of our ſelves than we ought to think</hi> when we compare our ſelves with one another, wherefore God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing placed at ſuch an infinite diſtance above the Higheſt and Nobleſt of his Creatures, and there being nothing in them which is not in himſelf, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>manations of whoſe Power and Goodneſs they are, he cannot certainly be capable of ſuch a paſſion as this, upon any account of equality or Emulation, neither can he value himſelf upon a Compariſon, though with the firſt born of all the Angels of Light.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>Novelty</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>naccuſtomedneſs</hi> is another cauſe of Pride, Men are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly Proud of things they are not uſed to, but they that are born to great things, or have been long accuſtomed to them, Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſits lightly and eaſily upon them, and they have an Air of Complaiſance and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, in the middeſt of that Fortune which an upſtart cannot bear without contemning
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49557:15"/> and trampling upon others, and what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes eaſie by <hi>Cuſtom</hi> in the Gifts of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, does ſo by <hi>Conſideration</hi> in thoſe of the Mind, they are not accompany'd in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering Men with a bloty and a puffy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor, but with Humility and Affability they recommend themſelves, and ſhun the two equally dangerous and pernicious Rocks of Hatred and of Envy; and therefore in God who was infinitely Perfect and Happy in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from all Eternity, his Perfection was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſo eaſie and familiar to him, that as he cannot think too well of himſelf, ſo he does it not with any contempt of his Creatures that are infinitely below him, but only with a juſt, wiſe, and conſiderate approbation of his own Adorable and Immortal Being. So that here is another excellence of Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that it hath not only its root and ſpring in God, but that it is alſo in ſome ſort a breathing after his Likeneſs, an imitation of his Perfections, and a participation of his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which may be the reaſon why the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences of Divine Grace, do ſo <hi>willingly</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend upon the Humble Man, becauſe there is a <hi>congruity</hi> between them, they have a <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance</hi> and <hi>likeneſs</hi> to one another, and God delights to dwell in ſuch a Mind, as is
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49557:16"/> ſo true an Image of himſelf, and repreſents the candor, equability and conſtancy, of his unſhaken, peaceable and quiet Eſſence, and this makes it true in a Spiritual, as well as in a Natural ſenſe, that <hi>God reſiſteth the Proud, but giveth grace to the Humble:</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it any wonder to find in the Sermon on the Mount, that the <hi>Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> is promiſed to the <hi>Poor in Spirit,</hi> when it appears to be ſo <hi>Godlike,</hi> and ſo <hi>Heavenly</hi> a diſpoſition, for that which we call <hi>Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> in Men, is almoſt the ſame conſtitution of Mind, to which the happyneſs of the Divinity it ſelf is owing, that is, the <hi>Equabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, Ingenuity,</hi> and <hi>Quietneſs</hi> of his Nature.</p>
            <p>The Power and Juſtice of God are only terrible and frightful to conſider; we ſhrink and tremble at them with horror and amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for fear of Thunderbolts, and Hurri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canes, and Earthquakes, for fear the Sea ſhould break it's wonted Banks, and Heaven deſcend in Hailſtones and Coles of Fire; for fear of Plagues and Famins, and other <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demical</hi> Evils, knowing, as we do, how much he can inflict, and being ſenſible how much we have deſerved; but 'tis his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs only that excites our Love, that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flames and ſtimulates our Zeal, that <hi>harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizes</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:49557:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> and ſweetens our Devotion, that takes our Harps deſign from off the <hi>Willowes</hi> in the middeſt of all theſe Melancholy thoughts, and makes them joyn in conſort with <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thems</hi> of Praiſe. And what is true of God the Governor of all things, is true in its propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Kings too, and their Subordinate Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates and Miniſters; their Power when it is not temper'd with Sweeneſs and Benignity, may indeed extort and force Obedience from us, but it creates Hatred and Averſion at the ſame time; but when we diſcover a ſtroke of Goodneſs, a Pity in the middeſt of Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, a ſenſe and <hi>ſympathy</hi> of Humane Frailty, in the middeſt of the Severities they inflict upon us, we do not ſay then as <hi>Jacob</hi> did to <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi, Curſed be their Anger, for it was fierce; and their Wrath, for it was cruel,</hi> but we Kiſs and Embrace the kind and unwilling Rod, and praiſe it at the ſame in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, when we are ſmarting under it: And as this bleſſed, this even temper of Mind re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commends even God himſelf, and his Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerents to their Subjects, ſo it recommends their Subjects back again to them, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns with new Charters, new Priviledges, new and encreaſt influences of Divine Favor, and of Royal Goodneſs. Therefore let us
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49557:17"/> Pray for Humility, that Humility may Pray and Intercede for us, both with our God, and with our King.</p>
            <p>There is nothing more certain in experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, than that if two Men be equally Rich, equally Noble, and in equal Place and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in the State, and if the temper of the one be Humble, Affable and Kind, that of the other Severe, Moroſe, Implacable, Proud and Haughty, that the one of theſe ſhall be Reverenc'd and Eſteem'd, the other Deſpiſed by ſome, and Hated by all; and ſince Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es are of no other uſe, after the neceſſities of Nature are ſupplyed, than to procure us Power, Intereſt and Eſteem among Men, it is manifeſt in this caſe, tho' in an equality of Subſtance, of Land and Money, of Goods and Chattels, of Birth and Fortune, that ſtill, he that hath the greater Authority, is in truth and reality the Richer Man, ſo that this Humility, this <hi>Poverty</hi> of Spirit, is when all is done, the <hi>trueſt,</hi> and the <hi>moſt va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable Riches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as in the caſe of <hi>Riches,</hi> ſo alſo in that of <hi>Learning</hi> or <hi>Knowledge;</hi> if we ſuppoſe two Men equally learned, equally knowing, with this diverſity of temper between them, the conſequence of this will be, in a mutual
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49557:17"/> excellence on both ſides, that the one ſhall be admir'd and prais'd, reſpected and lov'd, follow'd, and pointed at, and crowded after, but the other ſcarce ever taken notice of, or regarded, to his infinite trouble and vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for this is the fate of Inſolence and Pride, that it is ſure to be affronted and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn'd, and yet there is nothing that is ſo uneaſie under it, or that bears it with great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Impatience and Reſentment. Though after all, ſince the uſe of Learning is two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, Firſt, To inſtruct and ennoble a Mans ſelf, and Secondly, To make him capable of inſtructing others, and of being a public Bleſſing where he lives: The Second of theſe Uſes, which is certainly the beſt and nobleſt, is loſt in the Arrogant and Aſſuming Man, for Men had rather be Ignorant, than be <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſterially</hi> taught, or be impoſed upon even by Truth it ſelf, commanding a Reverence, not for it's own ſake, by gentle and inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating perſwaſion, but upon account of the <hi>Brows</hi> and <hi>Forehead</hi> of its Teacher; ſo that after all, if we reſpect the true uſe of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, though there be an equal extent of knowledge on both ſides, yet the Humble on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is the truely, the uſefully, the beneficially knowing Man.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:49557:18"/>
            <p>But I ſpeak this only upon ſuppoſition, that there can be ſuch a thing as a very Proud and a very knowing perſon, at the ſame time, a thing which I can very hardly induce my ſelf to believe; for Humility is a temper that naturally leads to Knowledg by conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Coolneſs, by induſtry and patience by not only enduring, but loving, with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to be oppoſed and contradicted, by cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting its miſtakes and errors every Day, as <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> do their Nativities, by new thoughts, new occurences, and new events. Humility inſinuates it ſelf by ſlow and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, but ſure and ſteady Progreſſions, into the deepeſt <hi>Myſteries</hi> of Art and Nature; Humility climbes up to Heaven, and brings Heaven down by Teleſcopes to it ſelf, and makes the Stars fall down before it, like the <hi>Angels of God, aſcending and deſcending</hi> upon <hi>Jacobs</hi> Ladder, and that not in a <hi>Viſion</hi> as it was with him, but in ſome ſort of <hi>reality</hi> and <hi>truth.</hi> But Pride is impatient, and makes too great haſt to be Wiſe, it takes up prejudices and will not forſake them, it diſdains to be miſtaken, and therefore will not relinquiſh its Errors, it is impatient of contradiction, and therefore cannot be inſtructed; it Vaunts
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49557:18"/> and Magnifies it ſelf as having run through the whole courſe of Truth, when it hath ſcarce performed the neareſt Stage of that long, weariſome and laborious Journey, and that too with a very precipitant and haſty motion, for the <hi>Proverb</hi> holds good in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiries after Truth, that <hi>the fartheſt way a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout is the neareſt way home,</hi> and that a cool, humble, conſiderate, ſober pace, will with the greateſt ſpeed, and with the moſt certain and aſſured ſafety, conduct the Traveller to his Journies end.</p>
            <p>Of the truth of this, we have had a noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious inſtance in experience in this laſt Age of ours; in the late Famous and Ingenious Author of the <hi>Leviathan,</hi> I mean, who as appears by ſome of his Performances, was a Perſon qualifi'd by Nature for extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry things, had they not been unhappily pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by the Pride and Haughtineſs of his temper, he was got, it ſhou'd ſeem, into the <hi>Dogmatical</hi> Humor, and was impatient of Contradiction from others, though full of the Spirit of Contradiction himſelf, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to be the Founder of a new Sect that ſhould be called after his Name, as there are but too many of his Diſciples to be met
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49557:19"/> with, and he would needs be the Author and Inventer of new Notions and of new <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſes,</hi> whither the Nature of things would bear them or no; and from hence it came to paſs, that he became ſo blind, that he could not ſee the Sun at Noon-day; he could not diſcover, the exiſtence of a God, neither did he take the conſideration of him into the <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtem</hi> of his <hi>Politics,</hi> by which the main Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar of Obligation was deſtroyed; he was uſed to ſay, that the Laws of every Nation, were the <hi>only</hi> Law and Goſpel when all was done, and yet by his Principles he could at any time diſpence not only with Poſitive Laws, but with the Natural too, which are of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, Unalterable and Eternal Force; ſo that according to him, there is no ſtanding Nature of things, no principle of Conſcience, or of Obligation; and what a vaſt abſurdity in <hi>Politics</hi> this Doctrin is, what Miſery and Confuſion it would introduce among Men, whereever it is heartily Believed and Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced; a blinder Man then Mr. <hi>Hobs</hi> himſelf, though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e was blind enough, may eaſily diſcern: In his Natural Philoſophy he hath been Unanſwerably confuted and expoſed by ſeveral learned Men, and in his Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49557:19"/> too, ſo effectually taken to task, that it hath been demonſtrated plainly, that he never was more miſtaken, than when he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf pretended to Demonſtration; and when he wrote his Book <hi>Contra Faſtum Geometra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> againſt the <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Loftyneſs</hi> of the <hi>Mathematicians,</hi> he diſcovered his own Pride and Ignorance together; ſo neceſſary is Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility to Knowledg, ſo dangerous, nay ſo deſtructive to their deſign is it, for Men that would be Learned, to be Proud.</p>
            <p>And if we Tranſlate Humility from Arts and Sciences to matters of Religion; Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty though it do not <hi>Anathematize</hi> and Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, is almoſt every whit as able to determin Controverſies, as a <hi>General Council,</hi> and is as well qualified to preſide in the Divinity Chair, as any Univerſity <hi>Dictator</hi> of them all; Humility is a ſharp, inquiſitive and diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Vertue, and ſuch as perſwades the belief of what ſhe teaches, by very ſtrong Arguments, but by ſtronger temper; and Men are willing to give Ear to what ſhe ſays, becauſe they ſee plainly ſhe hath no deſign upon them, but only for their good; they know her to be a very ſhrewd and learned Vertue, that ſhe hath uſed great induſtry in her inquiries after
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49557:20"/> Truth, and that ſhe ſpeaks her Mind with all imaginable frankneſs and ſincerity, and with a deſire to ſcatter Knowledg and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyneſs together, which things of themſelves without much uſe of Argument, are a very fair ſtep to Conviction.</p>
            <p>But if ſhe cannot bring all Men to be of a mind, or if her own Subjects, the Vaſſals and liege People of the humble Kingdom, which is I am afraid no larger than the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritory of ſome <hi>Indian</hi> Princes; if theſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves cannot all be united into one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Faith, yet Humility conſiders Wiſely, that all Men have not, neither indeed can have, the ſame Capacity, the ſame Strength and Vivacity of Wit and Judgment, the ſame Opportunities, the ſame Education, the ſame Apprehenſions, and the ſame notions of things, and therefore admits a difference without a diſagreement. And this I am ſure of, it would be a bleſſed change, if <hi>Humility</hi> could take the place, and do the Office of <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical cenſures,</hi> ſo as to make them uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and needleſs for the future, and ſo put an end to thoſe ſeverities of Law, which, as all other puniſhments in other matters, can be juſtified by nothing, but only that they are
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49557:20"/> neceſſary, becauſe mad men run Opinion into Faction, and Faction into Riot and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion. And I dread to think how thin and <hi>depopulate</hi> the Kingdom of Heaven will be, and the <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> which is above, a City al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt without Inhabitants, and a Kingdom without Subjects, notwithſtanding all our pretences to Salvation, and our annexing it to this or that Communion, if none but the <hi>Poor in Spirit</hi> ſhall obtain it, if none but the <hi>Humble</hi> and the <hi>Charitable</hi> Man ſhall be Saved.</p>
            <p>Humility would not only prove a bleſſed Inſtrument of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> peace, but alſo of <hi>Civil</hi> too, if it could but gain Credit and Reputation among us; for Humility never complains before it is hurt, nay, Humility for the ſake, and for the good of her Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, rather than make a broil and a diſturbance in it, can ſuffer her ſelf to be hurt without complaining; ſhe neither thinks, nor does, nor apprehends any ill; ſhe is a Friend to all, and therefore thinks all to be a Friend to her; ſhe ſees no <hi>Fantaſtic</hi> and viſionary Dangers, ſhe is troubled with no imaginary Jealouſies and Fears, ſhe cannot diſcern Apparitions in the Air, nor Monſters in the Earth, nor
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49557:21"/> Whales portending calamities in the Water, but ſhe puts her firſt Truſt in God, and her next in the King, and ſhe believes that all things will work together for good to them that walk like her, and do their duty. She neither pries into the Cabinets of Princes, nor cenſures the tranſactions of State, nor raiſes falſe Reports to create an ill Opinion of her Governors, in the People, neither doth ſhe foment or encourage them when they are raiſed.</p>
            <p>Humility reſolves, let what will come to paſs, to be quiet and ſubmit, becauſe ſhe conſiders that the <hi>Hand</hi> of the <hi>King,</hi> is as the <hi>Finger of God, who doth whatſoever pleaſeth him both in Heaven and Earth, by whom Kings Reign and Princes decree Juſtice.</hi> Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility is a peaceable and reſigning Vertue, and wherever ſhe hath a Temple in any Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Breaſt, there the King hath a Faithful and Obedient Subject.</p>
            <p>But that which makes moſt of all for the commendation of Humility is, that our bleſſed Savaiour who was God incarnate, and who ſuffered ſo many indignities and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches from the worſt of Men, who hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled himſelf even to the Death, the ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:49557:21"/> and painful Death of the Croſs, for our ſakes, hath given us ſo great a pattern and example of it, <hi>learn of me,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>for I am meek and lowly in Heart, and ye ſhall find reſt unto your Souls.</hi> And on this very day when he entred into <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> with Accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations and <hi>Hoſanna's;</hi> though the People miſtook him for a Triumphant Prince, and thought their Victorious <hi>Meſſias</hi> was a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, yet it was indeed no more then the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph of Humility, over the Scorn and Malice of his Enemies, it was but a Prologue to his approaching Crucifixion, which was in truth his laſt and greateſt Conqueſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he Triumpht over Death and Hell; and ſo the Prophet <hi>Zachary,</hi> and out of him the <hi>Evangeliſt</hi> St. <hi>Matthew</hi> hath deſcribed the matter, <hi>Rejoyce greatly, O Daughter of</hi> Zion; <hi>ſhout, O Daughter of</hi> Jeruſalem: <hi>behold, thy King cometh unto thee: he is juſt, and having Salvation, lowly, and riding upon an Aſs, and upon a Colt, the foal of an Aſs;</hi> and if ſo great an Example as this, the Example of God putting on human Shape, almoſt on purpoſe, that he might ſet a pattern of Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and Humility to us, will not encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and recommend the Practice of it, I
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49557:22"/> know not what will, for I have nothing elſe to ſay, but that Humility is Humility, that is, that a Vertue ſo tranſcendently excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and great, can be compared to nothing but it ſelf.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag. 23. line 2. for</hi> deſign <hi>read</hi> down.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
